<?xml version='1.0' standalone='yes'?>
<manual>
<C1>&lt;h3&gt;Introduction&lt;/h3&gt; &lt;p align="justify"&gt; This documentation describes the key features of the RBC GIS server. Specifically, this documentation deals with the online data viewer and editor. Please note, administrative control is undertaken via logging onto the server and/or the GeoServer / Postgres applications and these applications have separate documentation. &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p align="justify"&gt; The documentation can be navigated using the links on the left and is divided up to allow you to easily identify a topic of interest. Please familiarise yourself with the fault notification system as this will allow you to obtain support should you have trouble using the application. &lt;/p&gt;</C1>
<C1S1>&lt;h3&gt;Server Background&lt;/h3&gt; &lt;p align="justify"&gt; &lt;/p&gt; </C1S1>
<C1S2>&lt;h3&gt;Reporting a Fault&lt;/h3&gt; &lt;p align="justify"&gt;Please use the following link to access the helpdesk for the GIS server -&gt; &lt;a href='https://geo.reading-travelinfo.co.uk/rock/helpdesk' target='_blank'&gt;GIS Server Helpdesk&lt;/a&gt;.  &lt;/p&gt; </C1S2>
<C1S3>&lt;h3&gt;Key Contacts&lt;/h3&gt; &lt;p align="justify"&gt; The RBC GIS server is managed internally with additional support provided by the Managed Service Provider (MSP). The current contacts are: &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p align="justify"&gt; &lt;b&gt;RBC Contact: &lt;/b&gt; Marc Allen &lt;br /&gt; &lt;b&gt;MSP Contact: &lt;/b&gt; Peter Brett Associates &lt;br /&gt; &lt;/p&gt;</C1S3>
<C2>&lt;h3&gt;Viewing Data&lt;/h3&gt; &lt;p align="justify"&gt; &lt;/p&gt;</C2>
<C2S1>&lt;h3&gt;Basic Tools - Moving Around the Map&lt;/h3&gt; &lt;p align="justify"&gt;The main viewer is split into four areas: &lt;ol&gt; &lt;li&gt;The Toolbar&lt;/li&gt; &lt;li&gt;The Map&lt;/li&gt; &lt;li&gt;The Attributes Table&lt;/li&gt; &lt;li&gt;The Sidebar&lt;/li&gt; &lt;/ol&gt; The toolbar provides a number of tools used to navigate and edit features on the map. These may vary between maps. Standard tools include pan, select, zoom and measurement tools, as well as shortcuts to the attributes table and editing tools. &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p align="justify"&gt;When the &quot;Move the Map&quot; pan tool is active, you can move the map by holding the left mouse button down and dragging to navigate. You can zoom by double clicking on the map or using the roller ball. You can also use the tools located on the left of the map window.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p align="justify"&gt;To the right of the map window is the sidebar. This contains the layer options, measurement results and other tools. Select these using the small plus buttons located on the right of the title bars. Note, the option open in the sidebar may also change by selecting certain tools in the toolbar.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p align="justify"&gt;The attributes table is minimised along the bottom of the map. It can be expanded using the small plus button located on the right of the attributes table title bar. To return to the map, click the small plus button on the map window title bar&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p align="justify"&gt;The image below highlights these key areas.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;img src="img/editor/basic_layout.png" hspace="5" vspace="5" width="75%" height="75%" alt="" /&gt;</C2S1>
<C2S2>&lt;h3&gt;Popup Bubbles and Attributes Table&lt;/h3&gt; &lt;p align="justify"&gt;&lt;b&gt;Popup Bubbles&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;img src="img/editor/popups.png" hspace="5" vspace="5" width="400px" height="400px" alt="" /&gt; &lt;p align="justify"&gt;The map can be configured to allow popup windows to automatically appear when single clicking on the map window. Popup windows may contain images, highlighting and links to both local and external email addresses.  If there are a large number of records or layers, you may wish to have greater control over which layer is selected and when. To adjust this, toggle the &quot;Enable Popup Bubbles&quot; button, located in the toolbar. The darker colour indicates that Popup Bubbles are enabled.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p align="justify"&gt;The popup windows are customisable by the administrator for a project but cannot be changed through the viewer. &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p align="justify"&gt;&lt;b&gt;The Attributes Table&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;img src="img/editor/attributes.png" hspace="5" vspace="5" width="75%" height="75%" alt="" /&gt; &lt;p align="justify"&gt;The attributes table is a key part of the viewer. It allows easy access to the information behind the data displayed on the map. &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p align="justify"&gt;The information in the attributes table interacts with that in the map window. If you select a record on the map and then navigate to the attributes table, you will find the selected record highlighted. Conversely, if you query the data in the attributes table, the data shown on the map will be filtered to match.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p align="justify"&gt;The attributes table provides a number of additional tools such as the ability to update a status, edit a record and delete a row.  Use the &lt;&lt; and &gt;&gt; buttons to scroll left and right through the columns.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p align="justify"&gt;In addition, there is another set of &lt;&lt; and &gt;&gt; buttons at the top of the attributes table (left and right of the query tools). These buttons allow you to scroll through the records in the table as a subset of the rows is normally shown (default is 15 rows).&lt;/p&gt;</C2S2>
<C2S3>&lt;h3&gt;Quick Views&lt;/h3&gt; &lt;img src="img/editor/quickviews.png" hspace="5" vspace="5" align="right" alt="" /&gt;&lt;p align="justify"&gt;The GIS server provides the ability to filter information to show only the specific data you wish to see. This is achieved using the attributes table, however, where there are a number of common filters- or &quot;queries&quot;- it may be convenient to use the predefined filters in the sidebar.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p align="justify"&gt;An example of predefined maps is shown on the right. To change view, simply select the relevant option and the map will refresh. This enables quick switching between views.&lt;/p&gt; </C2S3>
<C3>&lt;h3&gt;Editing Data&lt;/h3&gt; &lt;p align="justify"&gt;The GIS viewer application is designed to allow basis editing of layers however it should be noted that it is not intended to be a full fledged GIS application. The primary method of editing GIS data should remain the use of desktop applications such as MapInfo, ESRI ArcMap, AutoCAD, Quantum GIS and other proprietary software of specific data analysis such as water or acoustic analysis. &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p align="justify"&gt;Notwithstanding this, the GIS server provides an excellent platform for both the dissemination of data to staff who are not trained in the use of desktop GIS as well as the ideal way to collect basic information from this target audience. &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p align="justify"&gt;One of the primary benefits of the GIS server is that it allows users to view the data interactively rather than just a printed map. In some cases GIS is used inappropriately, creating printed plans without proper regard to cartographic rules; however the GIS server provides the ability to pan, zoom and interact with the data meaning that even a cluttered map can provide some benefit to a user.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p align="justify"&gt;Notwithstanding the point above, it is recommended that users pay attention to the basic rules of cartography when editing maps. Perhaps the following list highlights some of the key considerations:&lt;/p&gt; &lt;ul type="square"&gt; &lt;li&gt;Never show more information than needed (this creates cluttered maps)&lt;/li&gt; &lt;li&gt;Change the symbols used to display data rather than move data incorrectly*&lt;/li&gt; &lt;li&gt;Try to keep data updated&lt;/li&gt; &lt;li&gt;Where possible link data from existing processes to avoid duplication of work&lt;/li&gt; &lt;li&gt;Pay special attention to the use of hyperlinked data&lt;/li&gt; &lt;/ul&gt; &lt;p align="justify"&gt;*The server uses an XML based language called SLD to style the map. Basic options can be developed using the styler but more complex styles may require assistance to produce. It is important to note that a point should be located based on the location and not moved to deal with symbology issues at a particular scale (zoom). Your users may zoom in further than the current zoom and it would be incorrect if the point moves to a wrong location as they zoom in.&lt;/p&gt;</C3>
<C3S1>&lt;h3&gt;Adding New Records (on the map)&lt;/h3&gt; &lt;img src="img/editor/edittools.png" hspace="5" vspace="5" width="192" height="662" align="right" alt="" /&gt;&lt;p align="justify"&gt;Editing tools are provided in the map view, please note some layers will not be editable.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p align="justify"&gt;The toolbar provides a shortcut button which will open up the editing panel in the sidebar to the right of the map; you can also access this panel by selecting it manually.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p align="justify"&gt;The editing panel provides a number of tools and these are shown on the right.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p align="justify"&gt;&lt;b&gt;To add features, simply select the relevant geometry option, select 'Add Feature' and then click/drag on the map and the feature will appear.&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p align="justify"&gt;There are a number of geometric types available for insertion.  It is important to note that these are treated differently.  The geometric types used in the GIS viewer are:&lt;/p&gt; &lt;ul type="square"&gt; &lt;li&gt;Point&lt;/li&gt; &lt;li&gt;Line&lt;/li&gt; &lt;li&gt;Polygon&lt;/li&gt; &lt;li&gt;Shape&lt;/li&gt; &lt;/ul&gt; &lt;p align="justify"&gt;One example of the differences is that a point is anchored to a specific point on the ground and therefore, although the icon can be changed, the size of the point cannot be physically resized- it is a single point.  A polygon, however, can be resized, skewed and rotated.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p align="justify"&gt;Due to the different functions available for a specific geometry type it is important to pick the correct geometry type first.  Point and line are self-explanatory but the polygons require a little further explanation.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p align="justify"&gt;The polygon option allows you to create a complex polygon.  This is done by single clicking on each point at which you wish to place a vertex and then double clicking for the final vertex.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p align="justify"&gt;The shape option is a simple polygon which has a defined number of sides.  3 sides would give a triangle, 4 a square or rectangle, 5 a pentagon and this continues as the sides increase.  Setting the number of sides to 99 will give you a circle of reasonable definition.  Shapes are the only geometry type which is added by dragging on the map.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p align="justify"&gt;The feature will appear as a temporary graphic on the map and you can add as many as you like prior to saving; although &lt;b&gt;as usual it is recommended that you save regularly&lt;/b&gt;.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p align="justify"&gt;When you click the save button you will be shown a form allowing you to fill in the attributes for the new feature.  Given the possibility to add a number of features prior to saving; a map window is displayed on the right to allow easy identification of each feature when filling in the attributes.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p align="justify"&gt;Please note, the adding and editing of features is session based. This ensures you only see your own edits and allows the server to delete temporary features after a period of inactivity (&lt;b&gt;your session will time out after 30 minutes inactivity&lt;/b&gt;). Therefore, please save your edits regularly and do not close and reopen your browser prior to saving. The system has, however, been designed to copy edits when refreshing the page.&lt;/p&gt;</C3S1>
<C3S2>&lt;h3&gt;Editing Existing Records (on the map)&lt;/h3&gt; &lt;p align="justify"&gt;To add an existing record to your edit session so that you can change the geometry please select the 'Switch feature to editable' option and then click on the feature of interest.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p align="justify"&gt;The geometry type will automatically be selected based on the geometry type of the feature you select.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p align="justify"&gt;Once a feature is displayed in the edit layer you can move, resize, reshape and rotate the feature as required / permitted for the geometry type.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p align="justify"&gt;When done, select the 'Save Edits' button and you will be presented with the attributes for the selected feature. These will be pre-populated with the record's attributes.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p align="justify"&gt;Make any changes to the attributes as required and then save the edits. This will then update the original feature and the map can be refreshed to update the symbols on the map.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p align="justify"&gt;Please note, if you wish to edit the attributes only, please use the select feature tool from the toolbar above the map then switch to the attributes table and use the edit function provided.&lt;/p&gt;</C3S2>
<C3S3>&lt;h3&gt;Editing in the Attributes Table&lt;/h3&gt; &lt;p align="justify"&gt;The attributes table allows a number of editing options, these being:&lt;/p&gt; &lt;ul type="square"&gt; &lt;li&gt;Quick updates for status field&lt;/li&gt; &lt;li&gt;Full attributes edit&lt;/li&gt; &lt;li&gt;Deletion of rows&lt;/li&gt; &lt;li&gt;Addition of rows (for non spatial tables only)&lt;/li&gt; &lt;/ul&gt; &lt;p align="justify"&gt;It is also possible to interact with the map window so you can apply filters to the table and they will be reflected on the map. Similarly, selecting a record on the map will cause the attributes table to highlight the record.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;img src="img/editor/attributeedit.png" hspace="5" vspace="5" width="546" height="351" alt="" /&gt; &lt;p align="justify"&gt;When a table has a status field it is possible to set up a quick update function. This displays a drop down box on the left of each row that provides the status options of each row. Changing the option will display a button which allows the status field to be updated without changing other fields.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p align="justify"&gt;If you need to change more than just the status field then the update row tool can be used to edit the full attributes for a particular row.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p align="justify"&gt;There is also a delete row tool available. This does back up the data prior to deleting the row but they can only be restored from the backup by an administrator so please be careful with this tool.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p align="justify"&gt;Some tables provide further attributes which may be linked to multiple spatial tables (i.e. those which are displayed on a map). These tables may not have geometry associated with them and examples may include lookups and external data tables. In some cases the add row tool may be enabled allowing you to add a record and then fill in the attributes but for the most part new rows / features are added using the edit tools in the map window.&lt;/p&gt;</C3S3>
<C4>&lt;h3&gt;Querying Data&lt;/h3&gt; &lt;p align="justify"&gt;The GIS server allows a variety of methods to enable the creation of subsets of data using query tools.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p align="justify"&gt;There are a number of query languages that apply to the GIS data, these include SQL for database tables, CQL for GeoServer data and URL strings which allow these queries to be passed between the various web pages. When developing a query this is normally done using SQL or CQL but it is important to note there are limitations to the CQL query language. Where a query can not be translated into a valid CQL, the table will be filtered but the map will not be filtered. This is to avoid errors which might cause the map to crash.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p align="justify"&gt;If you query the data in the attributes table, the data shown on the map will be filtered to match (where possible).&lt;/p&gt;</C4>
<C4S1>&lt;h3&gt;Basic Searches&lt;/h3&gt; &lt;p align="justify"&gt;The primary method for filtering data is provided as part of the attribute table tools. There is an image at the bottom of this page which shows the key steps described on this page.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p align="justify"&gt;The filtering tools can be found in the bar located at the top of the attributes table. To apply a filter, select a column from the 'Filter by Column' option.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p align="justify"&gt;This will bring up a set of filtering options and these are:&lt;/p&gt; &lt;ul type="square"&gt; &lt;li&gt;Equal to&lt;/li&gt; &lt;li&gt;Not equal to&lt;/li&gt; &lt;li&gt;Greater than&lt;/li&gt; &lt;li&gt;Less than&lt;/li&gt; &lt;li&gt;Greater than or equal &lt;/li&gt; &lt;li&gt;Less than or equal&lt;/li&gt; &lt;li&gt;Equal to the following pattern&lt;/li&gt; &lt;li&gt;Between these two values&lt;/li&gt; &lt;/ul&gt; &lt;p align="justify"&gt;These are mostly self explanatory however the pattern search is the explained in the 'Searching by Wildcard' section.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p align="justify"&gt;Enter the required values in the box provided without quotations and then use the 'Next Step' button provided.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p align="justify"&gt;The filter string will appear on the left with the option to apply the filter. Use the button to apply the filter to the table.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p align="justify"&gt;Buttons are available on the right of the top bar which allows you to return to the map (which should be filtered) or to remove the filter.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;img src="img/editor/query.png" width="100%" height="100%" alt="" /&gt;</C4S1>
<C4S2>&lt;h3&gt;Searching by Wildcard&lt;/h3&gt; &lt;p align="justify"&gt;The search by pattern option in the filter / query options allows you to search by text string but also to use wildcard characters.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p align="justify"&gt;A wildcard character is a symbol which represents an unknown section of text. There are two key types:&lt;/p&gt; &lt;ul type="square"&gt; &lt;li&gt;Missing Character = ?&lt;/li&gt; &lt;li&gt;Missing Section of Text = %&lt;/li&gt; &lt;/ul&gt; &lt;p align="justify"&gt;Adding one of these wildcard characters allows you to search for partially known strings and the following examples show how these should be used:&lt;/p&gt; &lt;ul type="square"&gt; &lt;li&gt;RG? ??H - Would return all postcodes starting with RG and ending with H&lt;/li&gt; &lt;li&gt;Cycle% - Would return 'Cycle Hire', 'Cycle Hub' etc&lt;/li&gt; &lt;/ul&gt;</C4S2>
<C4S3>&lt;h3&gt;Multiple Searches&lt;/h3&gt; &lt;p align="justify"&gt;Apply a basic filter as per the instruction in the 'Basic Searches' topic.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p align="justify"&gt;When the filter string appears on the left with the option to apply the filter use the 'Filter by Column' option to add further options to the existing filter.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p align="justify"&gt;The webpage will attempt to guess the order of your filters (i.e. whether this is an AND or an OR option).&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p align="justify"&gt;Use the button to apply the filter to the table.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p align="justify"&gt;Buttons are available on the right of the top bar which allows you to return to the map (which should be filtered) or to remove the filter.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;img src="img/editor/query.png" width="100%" height="100%" alt="" /&gt;</C4S3>
<C4S4>&lt;h3&gt;Search Limitations&lt;/h3&gt; &lt;p align="justify"&gt; &lt;/p&gt;</C4S4>
<C5>&lt;h3&gt;Additional Features&lt;/h3&gt; &lt;p align="justify"&gt;In addition to the basic functions of the GIS server viewer there are a number of extra tools to help make working with data more efficient.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p align="justify"&gt;This section describes the various tools that are provided.&lt;/p&gt;</C5>
<C5S1>&lt;h3&gt;Controlling Layers / Multiple Tables&lt;/h3&gt; &lt;img src="img/editor/layercontrol.png" width="209" height="511" align="right" hspace="5" vspace="5" alt="" /&gt; &lt;p align="justify"&gt;The GIS viewer allows for numerous overlays to be added to each map. This may also result in multiple attribute tables. To allow easy access to the various layers there is a layer control tool located in the sidebar to the right of the map as shown.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p align="justify"&gt;The sidebar allows users to switch layers on and off.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p align="justify"&gt;Where there are multiple attribute tables these are displayed as a vertical stack of tables. Headings are included for each table.&lt;/p&gt;</C5S1>
<C5S2>&lt;h3&gt;Data Downloads&lt;/h3&gt; &lt;img src="img/editor/download.png" width="210" height="514" align="right" hspace="5" vspace="5" alt="" /&gt; &lt;p align="justify"&gt;The GIS server viewer allows users to interact with data rather than just viewing it. If something is unclear the user can zoom in and / or use the popup bubbles and attributes to interrogate the data further. Notwithstanding this, there are still times when the data will require further analysis and therefore there are some tools available to allow the download of data.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p align="justify"&gt;Although the GIS server does allow data to be exported in Microsoft Excel format this is a resource consuming export type. Therefore it was decided to export CSV files instead as these can also be readily shown in Excel.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p align="justify"&gt;The data downloads panel can be found on the right of the map and allows layers on the map to be downloaded as:&lt;/p&gt; &lt;ul type="square"&gt; &lt;li&gt;CSV - Text file compatible with Excel&lt;/li&gt; &lt;li&gt;Shape Zip - A zip file containing a shapefile for use in desktop GIS and CAD&lt;/li&gt; &lt;li&gt;Google KML - Data link for use in Google Earth&lt;/li&gt; &lt;/ul&gt; &lt;p align="justify"&gt;The Google KML file does not download the data itself but instead provides a linked layer in Google Earth. This means you will require access to the server and your password in order to view the data but also means the data will continually update. Google Earth is also able to display height and time data including animating data based on a timestamp.&lt;/p&gt;</C5S2>
<C5S3>&lt;h3&gt;Measurement Tools&lt;/h3&gt; &lt;p align="justify"&gt;One of the many advantages of an interactive GIS plan on the GIS server over a standard printed map is the ease with which measurements can be undertaken.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p align="justify"&gt;To facilitate this, there are two standard tools available which allow users to measure on the map. These are:&lt;/p&gt; &lt;ul type="square"&gt; &lt;li&gt;Measure a Line&lt;/li&gt; &lt;li&gt;Measure an Area&lt;/li&gt; &lt;/ul&gt; &lt;p align="justify"&gt;Both tools are found on the toolbar located above the map and are used by single clicking on the map and double clicking to finish a line or polygon.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;img src="img/editor/mline.png" width="558" height="511" alt="" /&gt; &lt;p align="justify"&gt;The image above shows a line measurement, please note the result is shown in the sidebar on the right of the map&lt;/p&gt; &lt;img src="img/editor/mpoly.png" width="558" height="511" alt="" /&gt; &lt;p align="justify"&gt;The image above shows an area measurement, please note the result is shown in the sidebar on the right of the map&lt;/p&gt; &lt;/C5S3&gt; &lt;C6&gt;&lt;h3&gt;Managing Maps (admin only)&lt;/h3&gt; &lt;p align="justify"&gt; &lt;/p&gt;</C5S3>
<C6>&lt;h3&gt;Managing Maps (admin only)&lt;/h3&gt; &lt;p align="justify"&gt; &lt;/p&gt;</C6>
<C6S1>&lt;h3&gt;Basic Map Management&lt;/h3&gt; &lt;p align="justify"&gt; &lt;/p&gt;</C6S1>
<C6S2>&lt;h3&gt;Config XML&lt;/h3&gt; &lt;p align="justify"&gt; &lt;/p&gt;</C6S2>
<C6S3>&lt;h3&gt;User Management&lt;/h3&gt; &lt;p align="justify"&gt; &lt;/p&gt;</C6S3>
<C6S4>&lt;h3&gt;Controlling Tools&lt;/h3&gt; &lt;p align="justify"&gt; &lt;/p&gt;</C6S4>
</manual>
