<?xml version='1.0' standalone='yes'?>
<manual>
<C1>&lt;h3&gt;Introduction&lt;/h3&gt; &lt;p align="justify"&gt; This documentation describes the key features of the RBC GIS server. Specifically, this documentation deals with the online data viewer and editor. Please note, administrative control is undertaken via logging onto the server and/or the GeoServer / Postgres applications and these applications have separate documentation. &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p align="justify"&gt; The documentation can be navigated using the links on the left and is divided up to allow you to easily identify a topic of interest. Please familiarise yourself with the fault notification system as this will allow you to obtain support should you have trouble using the application. &lt;/p&gt;</C1>
<C1S2>&lt;h3&gt;Reporting a Fault&lt;/h3&gt; &lt;p align="justify"&gt;Please use the following link to access the helpdesk for the GIS server -&gt; &lt;a href='https://geo.reading-travelinfo.co.uk/rock/helpdesk' target='_blank'&gt;GIS Server Helpdesk&lt;/a&gt;.  &lt;/p&gt; </C1S2>
<C1S3>&lt;h3&gt;Key Contacts&lt;/h3&gt; &lt;p align="justify"&gt; The RBC GIS server is managed internally with additional support provided by the Managed Service Provider (MSP). The current contacts are: &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p align="justify"&gt; &lt;b&gt;RBC Contact: &lt;/b&gt; Marc Allen &lt;br /&gt; &lt;b&gt;MSP Contact: &lt;/b&gt; Peter Brett Associates &lt;br /&gt; &lt;/p&gt;</C1S3>
<C2>&lt;h3&gt;Viewing Data&lt;/h3&gt; &lt;p align="justify"&gt; &lt;/p&gt;</C2>
<C2S1>&lt;h3&gt;Basic Tools - Moving Around the Map&lt;/h3&gt; &lt;p align="justify"&gt;The main viewer is split into four areas: &lt;ol&gt; &lt;li&gt;The Toolbar&lt;/li&gt; &lt;li&gt;The Map&lt;/li&gt; &lt;li&gt;The Attributes Table&lt;/li&gt; &lt;li&gt;The Sidebar&lt;/li&gt; &lt;/ol&gt; The toolbar provides a number of tools used to navigate and edit features on the map. These may vary between maps. Standard tools include pan, select, zoom and measurement tools, as well as shortcuts to the attributes table and editing tools. &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p align="justify"&gt;When the &quot;Move the Map&quot; pan tool is active, you can move the map by holding the left mouse button down and dragging to navigate. You can zoom by double clicking on the map or using the roller ball. You can also use the tools located on the left of the map window.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p align="justify"&gt;To the right of the map window is the sidebar. This contains the layer options, measurement results and other tools. Select these using the small plus buttons located on the right of the title bars. Note, the option open in the sidebar may also change by selecting certain tools in the toolbar.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p align="justify"&gt;The attributes table is minimised along the bottom of the map. It can be expanded using the small plus button located on the right of the attributes table title bar. To return to the map, click the small plus button on the map window title bar&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p align="justify"&gt;The image below highlights these key areas.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;img src="img/viewer/basic_layout.png" hspace="5" vspace="5" width="75%" height="75%" alt="" /&gt;</C2S1>
<C2S3>&lt;h3&gt;Quick Views&lt;/h3&gt; &lt;img src="img/viewer/quickviews.png" hspace="5" vspace="5" align="right" alt="" /&gt;&lt;p align="justify"&gt;The GIS server provides the ability to filter information to show only the specific data you wish to see. This is achieved using the attributes table, however, where there are a number of common filters- or &quot;queries&quot;- it may be convenient to use the predefined filters in the sidebar.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p align="justify"&gt;An example of predefined maps is shown on the right. To change view, simply select the relevant option and the map will refresh. This enables quick switching between views.&lt;/p&gt; </C2S3>
<C4>&lt;h3&gt;Querying Data&lt;/h3&gt; &lt;p align="justify"&gt;The GIS server allows a variety of methods to enable the creation of subsets of data using query tools.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p align="justify"&gt;There are a number of query languages that apply to the GIS data, these include SQL for database tables, CQL for GeoServer data and URL strings which allow these queries to be passed between the various web pages. When developing a query this is normally done using SQL or CQL but it is important to note there are limitations to the CQL query language. Where a query can not be translated into a valid CQL, the table will be filtered but the map will not be filtered. This is to avoid errors which might cause the map to crash.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p align="justify"&gt;If you query the data in the attributes table, the data shown on the map will be filtered to match (where possible).&lt;/p&gt;</C4>
<C4S1>&lt;h3&gt;Basic Searches&lt;/h3&gt; &lt;p align="justify"&gt;The primary method for filtering data is provided as part of the attribute table tools. There is an image at the bottom of this page which shows the key steps described on this page.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p align="justify"&gt;The filtering tools can be found in the bar located at the top of the attributes table. To apply a filter, select a column from the 'Filter by Column' option.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p align="justify"&gt;This will bring up a set of filtering options and these are:&lt;/p&gt; &lt;ul type="square"&gt; &lt;li&gt;Equal to&lt;/li&gt; &lt;li&gt;Not equal to&lt;/li&gt; &lt;li&gt;Greater than&lt;/li&gt; &lt;li&gt;Less than&lt;/li&gt; &lt;li&gt;Greater than or equal &lt;/li&gt; &lt;li&gt;Less than or equal&lt;/li&gt; &lt;li&gt;Equal to the following pattern&lt;/li&gt; &lt;li&gt;Between these two values&lt;/li&gt; &lt;/ul&gt; &lt;p align="justify"&gt;These are mostly self explanatory however the pattern search is the explained in the 'Searching by Wildcard' section.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p align="justify"&gt;Enter the required values in the box provided without quotations and then use the 'Next Step' button provided.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p align="justify"&gt;The filter string will appear on the left with the option to apply the filter. Use the button to apply the filter to the table.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p align="justify"&gt;Buttons are available on the right of the top bar which allows you to return to the map (which should be filtered) or to remove the filter.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;img src="img/viewer/query.png" width="100%" height="100%" alt="" /&gt;</C4S1>
<C5>&lt;h3&gt;Additional Features&lt;/h3&gt; &lt;p align="justify"&gt;In addition to the basic functions of the GIS server viewer there are a number of extra tools to help make working with data more efficient.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p align="justify"&gt;This section describes the various tools that are provided.&lt;/p&gt;</C5>
<C5S2>&lt;h3&gt;Data Downloads&lt;/h3&gt; &lt;img src="img/viewer/download.png" width="210" height="514" align="right" hspace="5" vspace="5" alt="" /&gt; &lt;p align="justify"&gt;The GIS server viewer allows users to interact with data rather than just viewing it. If something is unclear the user can zoom in and / or use the popup bubbles and attributes to interrogate the data further. Notwithstanding this, there are still times when the data will require further analysis and therefore there are some tools available to allow the download of data.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p align="justify"&gt;Although the GIS server does allow data to be exported in Microsoft Excel format this is a resource consuming export type. Therefore it was decided to export CSV files instead as these can also be readily shown in Excel.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p align="justify"&gt;The data downloads panel can be found on the right of the map and allows layers on the map to be downloaded as:&lt;/p&gt; &lt;ul type="square"&gt; &lt;li&gt;CSV - Text file compatible with Excel&lt;/li&gt; &lt;li&gt;Shape Zip - A zip file containing a shapefile for use in desktop GIS and CAD&lt;/li&gt; &lt;li&gt;Google KML - Data link for use in Google Earth&lt;/li&gt; &lt;/ul&gt; &lt;p align="justify"&gt;The Google KML file does not download the data itself but instead provides a linked layer in Google Earth. This means you will require access to the server and your password in order to view the data but also means the data will continually update. Google Earth is also able to display height and time data including animating data based on a timestamp.&lt;/p&gt;</C5S2>
<C5S3>&lt;h3&gt;Measurement Tools&lt;/h3&gt; &lt;p align="justify"&gt;One of the many advantages of an interactive GIS plan on the GIS server over a standard printed map is the ease with which measurements can be undertaken.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p align="justify"&gt;To facilitate this, there are two standard tools available which allow users to measure on the map. These are:&lt;/p&gt; &lt;ul type="square"&gt; &lt;li&gt;Measure a Line&lt;/li&gt; &lt;li&gt;Measure an Area&lt;/li&gt; &lt;/ul&gt; &lt;p align="justify"&gt;Both tools are found on the toolbar located above the map and are used by single clicking on the map and double clicking to finish a line or polygon.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;img src="img/viewer/mline.png" width="558" height="511" alt="" /&gt; &lt;p align="justify"&gt;The image above shows a line measurement, please note the result is shown in the sidebar on the right of the map&lt;/p&gt; &lt;img src="img/viewer/mpoly.png" width="558" height="511" alt="" /&gt; &lt;p align="justify"&gt;The image above shows an area measurement, please note the result is shown in the sidebar on the right of the map&lt;/p&gt; &lt;/C5S3&gt; &lt;C6&gt;&lt;h3&gt;Managing Maps (admin only)&lt;/h3&gt; &lt;p align="justify"&gt; &lt;/p&gt;</C5S3>
</manual>
